Translations mss., 1800-2010 LMC 2245
Lilly Library
Translations mss.
1800-2010
Lilly Library
LMC 2245
2 Boxes 2 standard
1 bound
Translations mss., ca. 19th-21st centuries, consist primarily of manuscripts of literary translations, either from a foreign language into English or in some cases from English into another language. Also present are letters from authors to translators of their work or from the translators to the authors they translate.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by translator's last name.
Scope and Content Note
Tranlations mss., ca. 19th-21st centuries, consists primarily of manuscripts of literary translations, either into English from another language or from English into another language. Also present are translators' letters related to their translations. Items have been collected over time either as gifts or purchased from a variety of sources.
Acquisition Information
Gift/purchase: 2001-2007
Literature--translating; Corman, Cid; Stewart, Philip, 1940-; Kunitz, Stanley, 1905-2006; Borges, Jorge Luis, 1899-1986.; Maḥfūẓ, Najīb, 1911-2006; Bly, Robert; Rabassa, Gregory; Weisstein, Ulrich
- Translations mss.
  - Alsebail, Abdulaziz.Poems from Korea. Saudi Arabia: Korean Consulate, 1995., Inscribed copy of bilingual edition in Arabic and English. Accompanied by annotated photocopies of corrected manuscripts used in preparing the volume. (Box 1)
  - Bly, Robert.The Cat-Trip. English translation, ca. 1964-65, of Katt-Resan: bilderbok by Ivar Arosenius. (Stolkholm: Albert Bonniers Förlag, 1963.), Typed translations of the captions mounted above the original Swedish in the printed volume; title page translated and signed by Robert Bly. (Box 1)
  - Corman, Cid. English translation of Luis Borges, "The Word of God.", Translation based on French version by Roger Caillois rather than from the original Spanish story. Title changed in pencil from "The Signature of God"; some typed and holograph corrections. (Box 1)
  - Day, Mark Tyler. English translation from the Arabic of Edwâr al-Kharrât, "The Railway Station.", Xerox of the original Arabic text as published; Xerox of the original Arabic text line by line, with a draft of the interlinear translation into English, with queries and revisions; Xerox of final English version; Xerox of translator's "Prefatory Essay." (Box 1)
  - Fennell, Hannah Fisher. "Zuma or the Discovery of Bark" by the Countess de Genlis., Translated from the French by Suzanne Stefania d'Albiac, and into English from the Italian, by Hannah Fisher Fennell, 1830. Bound in contemporary calf, marbled boards. Pencil signature of Rebecca H. Coates, 1840, on front blank leaf. (Box 1)
  - Garikano, Anton. Translation into Basque of Toni Morrison's Beloved., Computer printout, 3rd draft. Inscribed by the translator "for Breon [Mitchell], 28-VIII-2003." Includes six pages of translator's computer notes raising questions about the English text and comparing trial Basque versions with English and the published French translation. (Box 1)
  - Kedierski, Marek.Końcowka. Translation into Polish of Samuel Beckett, "Endgame.", Includes translator's revisions. Presentation copy to Breon Mitchell, Aug. 19, 1982. This version was done for a performance at the Stary Teatr in Krakow, Poland, in 1981. (Box 1)
  - Kunitz, Stanley. Tranlations of Giuseppe Ungaretti's "La Morte Meditata" (Meditations on Death) and "Canzone descrive lo stato d'animo del poeta" (Canzone Descriptive of the Poet's Spiritual State)., Corrected typescripts, titled in holograph and signed by Kunitz. (Box 1)
  - Manheim, Ralph., Two cassettes. Tape of literary translator Ralph Manheim (1907-1992) interviewed by Lillian Friedberg. (Box 2)
  - Stewart, Philip. Translation from the Arabic of "Children of Gebelawi" by Naguib Mahfouz., Complete early draft, ca. 1960s, of the novel; revised throughout by the translator. (Box 2)
  - Rabassa, Gregory. Letters to William Claire, 1971-1973., Ten letters and one Christmas card from literary translator Gregory Rabassa to editor and publisher William Claire. Rabassa writes to Claire about his work translating Brazilian writer Dalton Trevisan, Mario Vargas Llosa, and Gabriel García Márquez. (Box 2)
  - "The Belle." English translation from the German of J.F.C. Schiller, ca 1860., Removed from Schiller, The Song of the Bell and Other Poems (Lilly PT2466 .G5 1854) (Box 2)
  - Weisstein, Ulrich. English translation of Achim von Arnim's "Die Majoratsherre," titled here "Lords of the Entail.", Final version, October 2000. Heavily revised and annotated throughout by translator. (Box 2)
  - Ben-Baruch, Bruria. Translation into Hebrew of Paul Auster's The Book of Illusions., Typescript and two sets of galleys with revisions by the translator and by Moshe Ron. (Box 3)
  - Wright, Barbara. Correspondence with Jean-Francois Hangouet, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Seidensticker, Edward. Binder containing correspondence and New Year's cards from Edward Seidensticker to Yasuko Ito Watt, as well as an audiotape of Watt's interview of Seidensticker and a guide to annotations within Seidensticker's 24-volume set of Nagai Kafu zenshu, 1984-1997 (Bound 1)
  - Letters from Manuel Puig to Marian Skedgell, 1970-1975
  - Letters from Gunter Grass to William Jovanovich, 1977-1987